字幕仅供翻译学习交流使用 禁止用于商业用途
本字幕由 发烧碟屋DTS-DEMO 原创翻译
片名：《帝国双璧》
太阳没有阳光
As incomplete as the sun without rays...
芬芳没有风吹
And fragrance without breeze...
就像没有统治者的帝国，皆不完整
ls a ruler without his Prime Minister.
我们的宰相 巴拉吉·维什瓦纳特佩什瓦的死
The demise of our Prime Minister, Peshwa Balaji Vishwanath...
给我们留下了一个紧迫的问题
Leaves us with a pressing question.
这大殿之上，有谁认为自己 有能力成为下一任佩什瓦吗？
Who here considers himself worthy enough to be the next Peshwa?
陛下，臣若有这个荣幸 吾愿接受佩什瓦一职
I would accept the post of Peshwa with great honour, Your Majesty.
潘·普拉提尼，你的提议很不错
Your proposal pleases me, Panth Pratinidhi.
朝廷上的各位是否赞同？
Does the court approve?
陛下...
Your Majesty...
唯一能保护马拉地帝国
The only man that can protect..
维持佩什瓦荣誉的人...
..the Maratha empire and preserve the honour of the Peshwa's post...
就是巴拉吉！
is Bajirao!
请原谅，陛下 这等言论是在嘲笑朝廷
Forgive me, Your Majesty but this statement mocks the court.
部长，似乎只有你一个人在笑
You appear to be the only one laughing, Minister.
每个人都有权证明自己的价值
Every man has the right to prove his merit.
仅仅是戴着父亲的头巾 并不代表他就继承了父亲的智慧
A son does not inherit his father's wisdom simply by wearing his turban.
就连檀香树也需要好几年的生长 才能散发出香味
Even a sandalwood tree needs time to age before it produces fragrance.
但是最嫩的荆棘也会刺人 这你怎么说？
But even the youngest thorn can prick. What say?
永远不要质疑猎豹的速度 鹰的视角，和巴拉吉的剑
Never doubt the cheetah's speed, the hawk's vision and Bajirao's sword...
它们随时都可以将你蒙蔽！
They could outwit you at any moment!
在下，巴拉吉·巴拉德
I, Bajirao Ballad...
巴拉吉·维什瓦纳特之子 认为自己有能力胜任该职
Son of Late Balaji Vishwanath, consider myself fit for this post.
为此，我愿意经受任何考验
And for that, I am willing to pass any test.
巴拉吉，考验是必然的
A test there shall be, Bajirao.
但我会交由潘·普拉提尼来决定
But I shall allow Panth Pratinidhi to decide it.
巴拉吉，通过将孔雀羽毛射成两半 来证明你的射术
Prove your marksmanship by splitting that peacock feather into two, Bajirao.
让你的武器，证明你的智慧
Let your weapons speak of your wisdom.
现在，咱们就见识一下 猎豹的速度，鹰的视角吧
Now let's see some of that cheetah's speed and hawk's vision...
陛下，该项挑战是将孔雀羽毛 射成两半
Your Majesty, the challenge was to split the peacock feather into two halves...
而朝廷目睹到，羽毛仍然完整
And the court witnesses that the feather is still intact.
但是它比之前更短了
But shorter than before.
扒开泥土，你就会找到另一半了
Sift through the mud and you will find the other half there.
这已经证明了我的射术
That was proof of my marksmanship...
现在说说它背后的启发
Now for the thought behind it.
泥土代表印度，孔雀羽毛代表
That soil is India and that peacock feather is the tree..
扎根于德里的莫卧儿帝国
..of the Mughal kingdom with its roots in Delhi...
那支箭...
The arrow is...
就是马拉地帝国
The Maratha empire.
直接将其根斩断 再大的树，也将倒下
Strike at the root and even the biggest tree will fall.
佩什瓦，你很睿智！
You have a brilliant mind, Peshwa!
注视马拉地帝国的荣耀吧
Behold the pride of the Maratha empire...
正义，忠实的
The righteous and dutiful...
巴拉吉·巴拉德 佩什瓦
Peshwa Bajirao Ballad!
看呐！
Behold!
这个故事属于夏胡·马哈拉杰国王
This story belongs to an era in history...
统治马拉地帝国的那段历史
When King Shahu Maharaj held the reins of the Maratha empire.
当时的宰相是巴拉吉·巴拉德
And his Prime Minister was Bajirao Ballad.
他的剑快如闪电 如喜马拉雅山一般不可撼动
A sword as swift as lightening... A will as immovable as the Himalayas.
他部落的光芒照耀在他的脸上 他的眼中只有梦想
The radiance of his clan on his face... And only one dream in his eyes...
看到马拉地帝国的国旗 在德里的天空画出象征胜利的红色
To see the Maratha flag paint the skies in Delhi, saffron with victory.
10年里，因着巴拉吉的英明领导 政治手腕，和无以伦比的战略
In ten years, Bajirao had captured half of India with his leadership,..
他已经征服了大半个印度
..political prowess and unmatched battle skills.
巴拉吉勇猛的故事
Stories of Bajirao's valour made headlines..
从南部的尼扎姆 传到了北部的莫卧儿帝国
..from the Nizam in South, to the Mughals in the north.
我们应该完成西瓦吉的梦想
We shall fulfill King Shivaji's dream...
打败莫卧儿帝国 让印度成为一个印度教国家
..Defeat the Mughals and make India a Hindu state.
不同于敌人的珠宝和财富
Unlike the enemy's jewels and wealth,..
我们的珍宝是旺盛的血气 和随时准备牺牲的英勇
..our treasury is rich with blood, ready for sacrifice.
我们不论生死，都是马拉地帝国的人
We owe our every breath to the Maratha empire.
我们是敢于面对任何风暴的闪电
We are the thunder in the face of any storm...
亦是敢于面对任何闪电的火海！
And we are a sea of fire in the face of thunder!
巴拉吉·巴拉德已经打破了 所有失败的镣铐
Bajirao Ballad shall break away all shackles of defeat..
扬起了全面胜利的红旗
..and unfurl the saffron flag in victory.
音乐及导演：桑杰·里拉·布汗萨里
在巴拉吉挥舞着剑 改变印度版图的时候
While Bajirao was wielding his sword to change the map of India...
一个壮丽的宫殿，沙尼瓦瓦达宫
A magnificent palace, Shaniwar Wada,
以他的名义，在普纳被建造
..was being constructed in Pune, in his honour.
喀什，祈愿还没结束 你这是要去哪啊？
Kashi, where are you going in the middle of prayers?
巴努来了！
Bhanu has come!
哪个巴努？
Bhanu who?
是我儿时的一个朋友 我马上就接她一起回来
A dear childhood friend... I'll be right back with her.
快点回来啊！
Be back soon!
好，马上
Yes, right away.
喀什什么时候才能学会啊！
When will Kashi ever learn!
巴努，你什么时候到的？
Bhanu, when did you arrive?
你干嘛站在外面啊 你应该进去，一起祈愿的
And why are you out here, you should've come into the prayer service.
没事
That's alright.
我们好久没见了 你还好吗，喀什？
It's been a while since we last met. All well, Kashi?
巴努，这是什么时候的事？
Bhanu, when did this happen?
你丈夫怎么了？
What happened to your husband?
他被杀了
He was murdered.
谁干的？
BY Whom?
佩什瓦
By the Peshwa.
巴努，说话小心点！
Tread carefully Bhanu!
你这是在指控佩什瓦杀人！
You are accusing the Peshwa of murder!
他还被指控反间...
He was accused of being a spy...
佩什瓦不可能做出此等大逆不道之事
The Peshwa would never do such injustice.
这里面是什么？
What's in this?
佩什瓦的正义
The Peshwa's justice...
我丈夫的骨灰
My husband's ashes.
今天，你让你的家圣洁了
Today you sanctify your home...
然而我的家已被烧成了灰烬
While mine burns to ashes.
喀什，我很思念我丈夫
I ache for my husband, Kashi.
你也会的！
As will you!
大人，有一个从本德尔坎德来的士兵
My Lord, a soldier has come from Bundelkhand.
他送来了查塔萨尔国王的信
He has a message from King Chatrasal.
那个士兵想见你
The soldier wishes to meet you.
国王是想把他女儿嫁给我吗？
Does the King wish to offer me his daughter's hand?
他说，穆罕默德·班加萨的部队 已包围了他的城池
He says Mohammad Bangash's troops have surrounded his fort...
他需要我们的救援
And he needs our assistance.
土可奇，我们是继续打自己的仗 还是帮助国王？
Are we to fight our own battles or help the king, Tukoji?
我们必须去希拉尔贾
We must reach Siraunja.
让那个士兵走吧
Send the soldier away.
可是，大人，那个士兵 执意要见佩什瓦
But Sir, the soldier is insisting on meeting the Peshwa.
土可奇，退下！
Tukoji, leave!
是
Certainly.
如果我们攻下这个山谷 就能更快抵达
If we take this valley, we will reach quicker.
你不能见佩什瓦
You cannot meet the Peshwa.
拦住他！任何人不得入内
Stop him! No one must go inside...
潘，礼貌地把她送走
Panth, please send her away respectfully.
本德尔坎德正在危难关头
Bundelkhand is in danger.
拉其普特的众妃子和公主 皆已服毒自尽
The Rajput queens and princesses are poised to self-immolate.
我们需要你的帮助
We need your help.
本德尔坎德有你这样的利器 还需要我帮什么忙？
When Bundelkhand has a weapon like you, what help should I be?
我现在帮不了你，请回吧
I cannot help you right now, please leave.
你可能会因此丧命
You may lose your life over this!
这已经不重要了
It hardly matters.
我在离开本德尔坎德时就发过誓
I swore while leaving Bundelkhand that..
要么带着巴拉吉 佩什瓦回去 否则就不回去
..l would return only with Peshwa Bajirao, or not at all.
大家让我相信你是个神 可你却连人都算不上
I put forth a plea believing you to be God, but you aren't even human.
你叫什么名字？
What is your name?
玛斯塔妮
Mastani.
我喜欢你的勇气和方式
I like your courage and your approach...
德坎普，潘
Decamp, Panth.
我们去本德尔坎德
We ride to Bundelkhand!
可是，大人，我们怎么跟陛下交代？
But Sir, what will we tell His Majesty?
陛下知道了会很高兴的
His Majesty will be happy to know that..
印度君主应该互相帮助
..one Hindu monarch is going to help another.
本德尔坎德离这有多远？
How far is Bundelkhand from here?
5天的路程
It's a five day march.
- 我们2天就能到 - 那不可能
- We shall get there in two... - That's impossible.
就让敌人们这样想吧
Let the enemy think that way...
玛斯塔妮，巴拉吉就是以速度闻名的
Bajirao's fame is carried by his speed, Mastani...
走吧！
Let's go!
最后的警告
Final warning...
“要么天亮投降，要么面对可怕的后果” 穆罕默德·班加萨
"surrender by daybreak or face dire consequences" - Mohammad Bangash.
还没有佩什瓦救援的信报
No word of help from the Peshwa.
那么我们只有2个选择了
That leaves us only two choices...
投降或牺牲！
Surrender or martyrdom!
牺牲！
MARTYRDOM!!
鲁哈尼女王！发生什么事了？
Ruhani Begum! What's going on?
陛下，如果敌军兵临城下
My king, if enemy breaches the fort walls...
女人们将屈服于这圣火 捍卫我们的尊严！
The women shall surrender to this fire, to safeguard our dignity!
陛下！
My king!
我看见东面有火光！
I see torchlights coming in from the East!!
肯定是玛斯塔妮带着救兵来了
That must be Mastani arriving with help.
将军！有一支军队从山那边过来了
General! An army approaches from beyond those hills.
转移大炮！
Swerve the cannons!
我们被骗了！向后转...后面！
We've been tricked! About-face... Head back!
这里没有军队...只有牛群
There is no army here... It's just cattle!
我们已经骗到了他们！
We have managed to trick them!
他们的大炮也已转移
Their cannons have been swerved.
玛斯塔妮，你通过秘密通道，进入堡垒
Mastani, reach inside the fort through the secret tunnel...
进去后就给我发信号
And signal me once inside.
我们就会准备好袭击
We'll be ready for attack.
玛斯塔妮！
Mastani!
父王，马拉地帝国的军队来了
The Maratha army is here, father.
- 本德尔坎德永远感激你 - 父王，我们之间无需感激
- Bundelkhand is forever indebted to you... - There is no debt in duty, father.
尽管去宣战吧，我会给佩什瓦发信号
Go ahead and declare war, I'll signal the Peshwa.
进攻！
Attack!
佩什瓦，祝贺你的胜利
Congratulations on your victory, Peshwa.
你和玛斯塔妮也是，她怎么样了？
I wish you and Mastani the same. How is she now?
受伤了，不过万幸
Wounded, yet grateful.
真不知该如何报答这份恩情
I don't know how I can repay this debt.
陛下，我不求奖赏
I seek no reward, dear King...
我只恳请您让我离开 我必须去希拉尔贾
All I ask for, is the permission to bid farewell. I must reach Siraunja.
这我不答应！
I won't hear of it!
你一定要跟我们一起庆祝胡里节！
You must celebrate this Holi (FESTIVAL OF COLOURS) with us!
公主，好像你真的要扮演胡里呢
My lady, it appears you've truly been playing Holi.
而且，肯定是跟佩什瓦一起了
And with none other than the Peshwa.
他抱着受了伤，意识不清的你回来的
He carried you here in his arms, wounded and unconscious...
即使是那个状态 你被他紧抱着，看着也不弱呢
But even in that state you were entwined with him as though one body.
祝贺你，公主，胜利的早晨
Congratulations on this victorious morning, My Lady.
我想和玛斯塔妮公主单独聊会儿
I would like a few moments alone with Mastani Saheba.
都退下吧
Leave us...
佩什瓦，这是我的私人寝宫 不是你战场
These are my personal chambers, Peshwa... Not your battleground.
没有我允许，谁也不能退下
One needs my permission to leave.
我说了，没有我允许，谁也不能退下
I said... No one leaves without my permission.
另外，单独和你在一起 可能会很危险
Besides, it could be dangerous being alone with you.
是吗？你不信任我吗，公主？
ls that so! Do you not trust me, My Lady?
恐怕是我不相信自己
I'm afraid it's myself I don't trust.
我拉其普特的血液 可能会使我对你的攻击进行复仇
My Rajput blood could make me avenge your assault.
你有权这么做
You have every right.
我的命是你的
I owe you my life.
你是我家乡的
I owe you my homeland.
玛斯塔妮，我甚至愿意把生命交给你
I would give even my life for you, Mastani.
看来，到底还是得私底下谈了！
It appears this account must be settled in private after all!
玛斯塔妮公主，你值得被称赞
You deserve to be praised, Mastani Saheba...
我的剑从未放过战场上的任何一个敌人
"My sword has never spared a foe on the battlefield,"
但是你却逃出了它的魔爪
..but somehow you escaped its wrath.
我想你伤的应该很重
I believe your wound is deep.
让我看看
Let me see it.
拉其普特人不会把伤口给别人看
Rajputs do not make a show of their wounds.
对别人来说，这也许是打仗留下的伤疤
To others, this may be a battle scar...
但对我来说，你是彩色的月光
But for me, you are the moon bathed in colour.
必须阻止毒素的扩散
The poison had to be stopped from spreading.
玛斯塔妮，我已经看到了你的伤口
I've seen your wounds, Mastani...
你已经不再是拉其普特人了
You are no longer a Rajput.
你看到的，不过是你剑的痕迹
What you see is merely the mark of your sword.
可流血的是我的心
But it is my heart that bleeds.
就算是佩什瓦也有心！
Even the Peshwa has a heart!
*在这彩色的节日
" On this festival of colours."
*为我涂上象征爱的红色
Paint me red in the colour of love.
*噢，淘气的你，就像克利须那神
Oh you playful one, like Lord Krishna.
*看着你，我仿佛被催眠
I'm mesmerized looking at you...
*抱紧我，而不要看着远方
Hold me close, instead of looking from afar...
*用你的双臂环抱我
Playfully you twist my arm...
*就像克利须那神与茹阿达那样
Like Lord Krishna with Radha.
*当我反抗，你拥抱我
And when I protest, you embrace me...
*你不肯放开我
You refuse to let go of me...
*我的脸刷的变红...那是爱的颜色
" Blushing I turn red... The colour of love."
天佑勇者，公主 毫无疑问，您就是勇者！
Fortune favours the brave, My Lady... And fortunate you are, indeed!
佩什瓦邀请您一起吃饭后差点
The Peshwa has asked for a paan (AFTER MEAL DELICACY).
你看，你正好有借口见他了
Here, it is your excuse to see him.
我已经不需要借口了
I no longer need excuses.
短剑？
This dagger?
这是佩什瓦给我的！
The Peshwa gave it to me!
天呐！你接受了？
Dear God! And you accepted it?
难道你不知道本德尔坎德的风俗吗
Don't you know that as per the custom in Bundelkhand...
女孩接受了男孩的短剑 就说明要嫁给他！
A girl is married to a man by accepting his dagger!
你接受了？
Did you accept it?
我接受了
I accepted it.
那他呢？
And he?
你的茶
Your paan.
如果我没醒呢？
And if I weren't awake?
那我希望这黑夜能永无止境
I would will the night to go on for eternity...
好让我永远地注视着你
And gaze upon you forever.
可那是不可能的
But that is impossible.
时间和命运，是无法被凡人掌控的
Time and destiny cannot be controlled by mortals.
不能被凡人掌控的 是被爱情的力量所统治
What cannot be controlled by mortals can be swayed by the power of love.
那爱能阻止太阳升起吗？
So can love stop the sun from rising?
它刚才已经阻止了
It just did.
喝你的查吧，不然我的殷勤就白费了
Do have your paan, or my hospitality might be questioned.
玛斯塔妮，我明天就要走了
Mastani, I shall be gone tomorrow.
为什么？
What of it?
也许我们将再也见不到了
Perhaps we may never meet again.
你就像祷告，永远在我心中
You are in my heart, like a prayer.
你的名字就是我所敬拜的
The mention of your name shall be my worship...
公主，佩什瓦要走了！
My Lady, the Peshwa is leaving!
本德尔坎德的所有人都去送行了 除了你
Entire Bundelkhand has gathered for his farewell, except you.
快啊，公主！
Come, My Lady!
这么傲慢，可不像你啊，公主
Such arrogance does not become you, My Lady.
你错把爱当作傲慢了
You mistake love for arrogance.
这是什么爱啊？他要走了，而你...
What sort of love is this? He is leaving, and you...
看着他走，会要了我的命
Watching him go will be the death of me.
老天不许你死！ 但是这样，送行仪式就不完整了
God forbid! But this meeting will be left incomplete.
一个不完整的送行 为另一个人留下了承诺
An incomplete meeting leaves the promise of another.
如果命运不允许呢？
And what if destiny doesn't allow it?
玛斯塔妮的命运由自己书写
Mastani writes her own destiny.
我们或许是欠佩什瓦的...
We may be greatly indebted to the Peshwa...
但是，国王，我拒绝 将我们的女儿送去普纳，作为偿还
But I refuse to send our daughter to Pune as an obligation, My King.
我明白我们的婚姻从未被社会认同
I understand that our marriage has never been valid in the society...
因为我是穆斯林，而你是印度教徒
Because I am Muslim and you're Hindu.
来普纳，也是我自己的决定
It is my own decision to go to Pune...
我已经接受了佩什瓦的短剑
I am wed to the Peshwa's dagger.
这是本德尔坎德的风俗 不是普纳的风俗
This is a custom in Bundelkhand, not Pune.
别忘了，那个佩什瓦是印度婆罗门教的 而你是穆斯林
And do not forget that the Peshwa is Hindu Brahmin and you are Muslim.
玛斯塔妮也有印度教拉其普特的血脉
Mastani has Hindu Rajput blood too.
她崇拜阿拉真主和克利须那神
She worships Allah and Krishna alike.
久德哈和阿克巴已以政治的名义 撇开了信仰的差异
Jodha and Akbar put aside religious differences in the name of politics.
玛斯塔妮也是如此，只是她是出于爱
Mastani is doing the same, but for love.
让她去吧
Let her go.
就算是这样！他也不会 把她娶为合法的妻子
Even so! He will never accept her as his legitimate wife.
茹阿达也没有成为克利须那神的妻子
Radha was never Lord Krishna's wife...
但他们的名字是不可分割的
But their names are inseparable.
是啊，但他们是神！
Yes, but they are Gods!
爱就是敬拜...
And love is worship...
他们不需要任何人的允许
For which one needs no permission.
愿神实现你的愿望！
May God fulfill your wishes!
永远祝福你！
Stay blessed!
*我美丽的爱情回来了
My beautiful love has returned...
赞美主
Praise the Lord!
公主，等一下
A moment, My Lady...
你还没有跟我姓 （马拉地帝国的习俗）
You have not taken my name this time. (MARATHI TRADITION)
为什么
Why, brother!
现在是新时代了！ 在新的宫殿，也有新的风俗
It's a new era! New palace, new customs.
为什么非要公主跟你姓呢？
Why must the lady always take the man's name?
这次你跟她姓 不然你就不能进新房了！
You take her name this time, or else no entering your new chambers!
但女人跟丈夫姓是风俗 But it is a custom for women to say their husbands‘ name...
任何钻石都不及柯伊诺尔钻闪耀
No diamond can match the Kohinoor's sparkle and grace.
除了巴拉吉，任何姓氏 都无法照亮喀什的脸
And no name but Bajirao's lights up Kashi's face.
太好了！
Very good!
这边请，佩什瓦大人
This way, Peshwa Saheb.
公主
My Lady...
你马上就要进新房了
You are entering your new chambers for the first time.
太幼稚了！
What childishness is this!
你可跟我发过誓哦
You swore on me...
所以，我没说，就不许睁开眼睛
So don't open your eyes until I say so!
你不相信我吗？
Don't you trust me?
相信一个战士？
Trust a warrior?
你永远不会知道，他何时会攻击
You never know when he may attack!
现在，睁眼吧
Now, open your eyes.
你觉得怎么样？
What do you think?
美极了！
Beautiful!!
这跟沙尼瓦瓦达宫的其他房间可没的比
This is nothing compared to the rest of Shanivaar Wada.
公主，告诉我
Tell me something, My Lady...
什么？
What?
我从你眼里怎么还能看见它？
How come I still see it in your eyes?
什么啊？
What?
渴望！
Longing!
因为是它，在你这么久不在的时间里 支撑着我的
Because it keeps me company in your long absences.
哎呀，怎么不见了？
Oh dear... Where is it?
什么？|
What?
你的小情人啊！
Your mistress!!
你的短剑啊！
Your dagger?
估计你都把它给忘了
Just as well you've forgotten it.
就我们俩的时候，就别挂剑了
It will no longer come between us.
我说你的短剑是你的小情人 冒犯到你了吗？
Have I offended you by calling your dagger a mistress?
我太多嘴了！
I talk too much!
查塔萨尔国王为我们送来了贺礼
King Chatrasaal has showered us with gifts.
很好
I am pleased!
这时候再好不过了
The timing couldn't have been better...
开支可以被抵消了
Expenses had been piling up.
这么说，帮助本德尔坎德 证明对我们来说是有利可图的
So helping Bundelkhand has proved profitable for us.
这是什么？
What is this?
你是谁？
Who are you?
我是查塔萨尔国王的女儿
This is King Chatrasaal's daughter.
我都不知道他有个这么漂亮的女儿
I wasn't aware he had such a beautiful daughter.
很高兴认识你
I'm very pleased to make your acquaintance.
我也是
As am I, thank you!
你叫什么名字？
What is your name?
玛斯塔妮
Mastani.
玛斯塔妮...真好听
Mastani... Beautiful name.
你父王有很多妃子 你是谁的女儿呢？
Your father has many wives, whose daughter are you?
鲁哈尼女王的
Ruhani Begum's.
这么说你是穆斯林
I see, you are a Muslim.
只是送贺礼，查塔萨尔国王
King Chatrasaal needn't have sent his daughter..
没必要让他女儿长途跋涉过来啊
..all the way here simply to deliver gifts!
你说是吧，池马基？
What say, Chimaji?
这把短剑是巴拉吉的！
This dagger belongs to Bajirao!
在本德尔坎德，我们有个风俗 女孩要嫁给送她短剑的人
In Bundelkhand we observe a custom where girls are wed to daggers.
在穆斯林和拉其普特之间，或许是的
Perhaps amongst Muslims and Rajputs.
但在佩什瓦的政体下 我们不接受这样的政治联姻
In the Peshwa regime, we do not accept such political ties.
但我已经嫁给他了！
But I am already married to him!
池马基，你先安排她住下吧
Chimaji, please make arrangements for her stay elsewhere.
回本德尔坎德之前，来见见我
Do meet me before you return to Bundelkhand.
亲爱的...
My dear...
如果你继续盯着我看 会对我心生邪念的
If you stare any longer, you will cast an evil eye on me.
我正在与它做抵抗呢
I am trying to remove it.
你要去打仗？
Going to war?
我已经决定了
I have decided...
下一次，要和你一起上战场
Next time, I shall accompany you to war.
不管别人怎么说
No matter what anyone says.
但是你不会骑马啊，你要怎么去啊？
But you cannot ride a horse. How do you expect to come?
我可以去马厩，坐上我的马 扬起马鞭
I'll go to the stable, mount my horse, crack the whip...
风驰电掣，喀什来了！
And be off like the wind. Here comes Kashi!!
我们还没到战场，你都已经开打了
We haven't even reached the battlefield yet and you've started.
那这个战士还需要什么呢？
What else does this warrior need?
一块地，两顿美餐，一片天空 一匹骏马，一把剑
A bit of land, two square meals, a piece of open sky, a steed, a sword...
还有我的喀什
And my Kashi.
加起来，一共27
Altogether, twenty-seven.
什么？
How so?
27处伤口
Twenty-seven wounds!
下次别让敌人靠你那么近了
And this time you let the enemy get too close...
为了避免第28个伤疤
And now to avoid the twenty-eighth wound...
这个戒指会保护你，不被邪恶之人
This ring will protect you from both the evil eye..
和敌人的剑所伤
and the enemy's sword.
公主，我觉得这些人不怀好意
My Lady, I do not trust the intentions of those people.
那根本就不是客人住的房间！
These are no guests' chambers!
他们这是在贬低你的身份
It's a strategy to demean you.
他们现在让你跟那些妓女住在一起
If they can put you up amongst courtesans,..
下次就敢叫你去厅堂上跳舞了！
..they can ask you to dance at their court next!
公主！
My Lady!
看这只蝴蝶啊！
Well, well... Look at the butterfly!
公主，把我们的士兵送回家 真的太不明智了
My lady, it was unwise to send our soldiers home.
我们现在异国，被陌生人包围
We are in a strange land, surrounded by strangers.
你永远不知道会遇到什么麻烦
You never know what problems might arise.
什么人会把客人安排的 跟妓女一起住啊
What kind of people would house a guest amongst courtesans.
这可是查塔萨尔国王的女儿啊
And that too the daughter of King Chatrasaal.
本德尔坎德的人要是直到 还不得举兵打过来啊
Swords would be raised in Bundelkhand if they caught wind of this.
你却还安静地坐在这...
Yet you sit here silently...
公主，我知道你感觉被羞辱了
I know you feel humiliated, My Lady.
我们回家吧，省的在这被羞辱
Let us return home rather than be insulted here.
如果他真爱你，佩什瓦 就会去本德尔坎德找你
If he truly loves you, the Peshwa will come after you, to Bundelkhand.
而且，不论你怎么努力
One more thing, no matter your efforts...
他们也绝对不会让他知道你在这的
They will never let him learn you are here.
我绝对不会让他们忘记我对他的爱
And I will never let them forget my love for him.
大人，您现在看到的是 沙尼瓦瓦达宫最华美的区域
My Lord, you are now witnessing the most beautiful section of Shanivaar Wada...
镜宫
The Palace of Mirrors.
哇，池马基
Whoa, Chimaji...
这太梦幻了！
It's unreal!
在您多年来，忙于征战的时候
While you have been busy fighting our enemies for years...
您的弟弟就在建造这个
Your brother has been building this.
池马基，你这是把泰姬陵 搬到普纳来啦
Chimaji, you have brought the Taj Mahal to Pune.
你应该今晚来亲眼目睹一下 这里真正的华美
And you shall witness the true splendor of this place tonight...
等我们庆祝新年的时候
When we celebrate the New Year.
弟弟，这的确像一个梦幻世界
Truly this is a dreamworld, brother.
这个梦幻世界真正的魔法 就在你的脚下
The true magic of this dreamworld lies in the wonder at your feet.
什么意思？
How do you mean?
巴拉吉，此时此刻，只要喀什想看
At this very moment Bajirao, if Kashi desires..
她在她的寝宫里，就能看见你和纳纳
..she can see you and Nana from her chambers.
你是说，喀什能从她的房间 看到父亲和儿子？
Are you saying Kashi can see both father and son from the comfort of her room?
那就是魔法所在！
Therein lies the magic!
那个莲花图形下有一个装置
That lotus has a mechanism that makes..
能让你倒影在这些镜子里
..your reflection shine from these mirrors...
直接投射到喀什房间的小窗户上
Straight onto the little window in Kashi's room.
公主！
My Lady!!
窗户上有一道光线
There's a beam coming through the window.
真的吗？
Really!
真的，快点，快去看啊！
Yes, really, come on, come quickly!
然后光线穿过玻璃，传到水面
Then traveling through the glass on the water,..
镜像就会呈现在她房间的窗帘上了
..it reflects onto the curtain in her chambers.
快点，公主，快点！
Quickly, My Lady, quickly!
等一下！
Wait a moment!
即使巴拉吉在镜宫 我们在这也能看见他
Oh! We can see Bajirao here although he's in the Palace of Mirrors.
好神奇啊！
It's magic!
看看我们的巴拉吉多英俊啊
Just look at how handsome our Bajirao is.
嘿！别色眯眯的看着他啦
Hey! Stop casting the evil eye on him.
妹妹怎么会色眯眯地看姐夫呢
A sister can never cast an evil eye on her brother.
不过我新说行政长官的太太们 都很想见他
But I've heard the Nawab's wives yearn to set eyes on him.
听说她们为了见他，连金子都愿意付呢
I've heard they would gladly pay his weight in gold for a glimpse of him.
要是想看，就让他们付钻石吧
Let them pay his weight in diamonds if they want...
我的巴拉吉，永远不会看别的女人
My Bajirao has never so much as looked at another woman.
明白嘛！
Understood!
*就像从天而降的天使
Like an angel descended from heaven...
Her tresses exuding a divine fragrance...
*她的长发散发出沁人的香气
Here she comes...
*她来了...金光闪闪
Here she comes... A vision in gold.
*我中了你爱情的毒
I am intoxicated by your love.
*我对你的爱，众人皆知
My love is no secret.
*全世界都想阻止我 但看看爱情把我带到了哪里
The world tried to stop me, but look where love brought me...
*他们说玛斯塔妮也中了你爱情的毒
They say Mastani is intoxicated by your love...
*你先是伤了我的心
First, you wounded my heart...
*然后又用你的爱治愈了它
Then, you healed it with your love...
*你的爱使我变得特别
" Your love has become my identity..."
*爱你就是我的决心
And loving you is my purpose.
*每个角落都被你的美所照亮
Every corner is illuminated by your beauty...
*玛斯塔妮，你的确是中了爱情的毒
You are indeed intoxicated by love, Mastani...
*你的灵魂是纯洁的 你的爱是神圣的
Your soul is pure and your love, divine...
玛斯塔妮，人如其名 一个用自己的韵律在舞蹈的人
You have been aptly named Mastani, one who dances to her own tune.
我很惊讶，也很高兴在普纳看见你
I'm surprised but happy to see you here in Pune.
这个...是我热情的象征
This paan... A token of my hospitality.
我们明天见
We shall meet tomorrow.
你的能力超出了我的想象
Your capabilities greatly exceed my expectations.
你是个有天赋的舞者
You are a talented dancer.
谢谢
Thank you.
想赞美我的话 就接受我与你们联合的请求吧
Please pay me a further compliment, accept my alliance.
我当然接受
Of course I have.
你现在以舞者的身份，与我国结盟
You are now allied with the kingdom as a court dancer.
很快，你就会到国王宫殿跳舞了
Very soon you will dance at the king's court in the capital.
你不喜欢我的礼物吗？
Do you not like my offering?
我感谢您送的每件礼物 但你这是在给你的儿子带上镣铐
I cherish your every offering, be it an anklet or a son...
你越是阻止他和我在一起 我就越接近他
The more you try to distance him from me, the closer I shall get to him.
那你就百折不挠地试试看
Then keep trying endlessly.
舞者的地方永远在王座之下 宫殿的地板上
A dancer's place is always below the throne, on the court's floor.
我总是被人称赞貌美...
I have always been complimented on my beauty...
现在能被一个
Today watching a woman of..
您这种身份的人威胁，是我的荣幸
..your standing threatened by it, makes me proud.
快点离开首都吧
Prepare to leave for the Capital.
看来还没人从昨晚的表演中清醒过来
It appears no one has sobered from last night's performance.
看看周围，没有一个人想干活
Look around, not a soul wishes to work!
哪种战士才能让美人低下目光？
What is a warrior before whom a beauty is not compelled to lower her gaze...
哪种美人才能让战士放下宝剑？
What is a beauty before whom a warrior is not compelled to lower his sword?
太棒了，说得好
Bravo, Peshwa!... Well said!
勇敢的池马基来了
The brave Chimaji is here!
池马基，你的出现代表 我们的活动已经被审查
Chimaji your presence indicates our campaigns have been audited.
结果是什么
What is the outcome?
本德尔坎德已经减少了捐助
Discounting endowments from Bundelkhand,..
这3次活动都没有增加我们的财富
..none of the three campaigns have enriched our treasury.
这你就错了，兄弟
This is where you are wrong, brother.
我们怎么没有？
How have we not been enriched?
首先，胜利的荣誉
First - the glory of victory.
第二，用失败羞辱了班加萨
Second - shaming Bangash with defeat.
第三，征收了德里的马拉地钟
Third - tolling the Maratha bell in Delhi.
第四，红旗再次飘扬在天空中
Fourth - the saffron flag once again stands strong against the blue sky.
赞美神
Praise the lord!
还有第五，和本德尔坎德 建立了一生的联系
And fifth - a lifetime's bond with Bundelkhand.
还有最后，我的阁下，这你忘了
And sixth, My Lord, you forget!
有像玛斯塔妮这么美的舞女 为我们跳舞
A splendid dancer like Mastani to entertain us!
池马基，在我们这么好客的地方 玛斯塔妮公主这样的女人根本不缺
Chimaji, see to it our hospitality towards Mastani Saheba is in no way lacking.
当然，你可以放心
Of course... Rest assured I will.
她就住在希拉巴格宫
She's lodged at Hirabagh Palace.
派信使告诉她，今晚我要去看她
Send a messenger to tell her I shall visit this evening.
那不可能
That won't be possible.
为什么
Why?
因为你今天就要去首都，阁下
Because you must leave for the capital today, My Lord.
我可以明天去
I can do that tomorrow.
陛下在等你，你必须按时赶到
His Majesty awaits you, you must present yourself there on time.
你...蠢货
You... Fool!
管好你的舌头，懂了吗？
Reign in your tongue... Understood?
去首都
To the capital!
（夏胡王萨塔拉行宫）
欢迎，巴拉吉
Welcome, Bajirao.
我们都等得不耐烦了
You were impatiently awaited.
遵从你的召唤，陛下
You summoned and here I am, Your Majesty.
我要为本德尔坎德的事恭喜你
Congratulations on Bundelkhand!
为了你的荣誉我铸造了这把剑
I had this sword of Afghan iron forged in your honour.
非常荣幸
I am honored.
国王陛下，请允许我用这把剑 让德里跪倒在你的面前
My King, now permit me to use this sword to bring Delhi to its knees before you.
政治上看现在不是攻击德里的好时机
This is not the right time to attack Delhi, politically speaking -
我的直觉告诉我现在正是时候，陛下
My instincts say now is the time, your Majesty.
德里现在沉溺在放荡声色中
Delhi is submerged in a haze of debauchery.
莫卧儿王朝已经失去了信仰
The Mughal emperor's court has lost his faith.
我们要平定南方的尼扎姆 然后向北攻打德里
We have to appease the Nizam in the South, to get to Delhi, in the north.
但还有对外政策要考虑
There is such a thing as political diplomacy.
首相有他的想法，佩什瓦
Minister has a point, Peshwa.
这一步必须在谨慎思考之后才能选择
That step must be taken after much forethought.
我们在今天的晚会之后 再讨论这个问题
We shall discuss other matters after this evening's soirée.
这把剑最好留在它的剑鞘里
This sword is best left in its sheath, Peshwa.
你已经去不了德里了，你打算 把它架在哪个敌人的脖子上？
Since you won't be going to Delhi, what enemy's neck would you place it on?
佩什瓦不缺敌人
The Peshwa doesn't lack enemies.
别动
Don't move.
你的脖子非常脆弱
Your neck is very valuable,..
甚至比环绕在上面的那串珍珠还精致
..and more delicate than this string of pearls around it.
你也知道，永远不要怀疑猎豹的速度
As you already know... Never doubt the cheetah's speed,..
鹰的视野，还有巴拉吉的剑
..the hawk's vision and Bajirao's sword...
它们随时都能击败你
They can outwit you any time.
玛斯塔妮公主为什么在这里？
Why is Mastani Saheba here?
你母亲派她来为今晚提供娱乐
Your mother has sent her as tonight's entertainment.
开始吧
Let the entertainment begin.
你是宫廷舞者，来这里为我们提供表演
You are a court dancer, here to entertain.
你却亵渎了宫廷
Instead you are dishonoring the court.
我没有亵渎宫廷，而是坚守 我自己的荣誉
I am not dishonoring the court, but upholding my own honour.
你是谁？
Who are you?
玛斯塔妮
Mastani.
她是来自本德尔坎德的礼物
She is a gift from Bundelkhand.
她利用新年表演的机会 放火烧了佩什瓦宫
She lit up the Peshwa's palace with her performance during New Year.
那是正常的
That was a valid occasion...
这只是个表演
This is but a soirée.
她不是宫廷舞者而是...
She is no court dancer but King..
查塔萨尔王的女儿 佩什瓦的客人
..Chatrasaal's daughter and a guest of the Peshwa realm.
看来是个很特别的客人
A rather special guest, it appears.
没错，首相
Yes she is, Minister!
多亏了她佩什瓦才活着
Thanks to her the Peshwa is alive..
多亏了佩什瓦，马拉地才存在
..and thanks to the Peshwa the Maratha realm is alive!
陛下
Your Majesty...
她不属于这个皇宫，请允许她离开
She does not belong in this court. Allow her to leave.
那个佩什瓦人说得对
The Peshwa is right.
你救了他的命
You have saved his life...
我要怎么报答你
How can I repay you?
你无法实现我的愿望，陛下
You will not be able to fulfill my wish, Your Majesty.
什么愿望是一个国王都无法实现的？
What wish is this, that a king cannot fulfill?
佩什瓦
The Peshwa!
我佩服你的勇气，敢在这里要求 马拉地王国最珍视的东西
I salute your courage in asking for what the Maratha kingdom values most.
但你可能会因为这个要求而受罚
But you could be punished for this demand.
我将自己的性命交于你的剑下 如果爱是罪过，那就惩罚我吧
I lay my life, at the sword of thee. If love is a crime, punish me!
但如果你扣留我的行为是错的 那就让我的名字像无名歌声一样消失
And yet, if thee hold me wrong, Erase my name like an untold song.
说得好
Well spoken!
你可以走了，玛斯塔妮
You may leave, Mastani.
不要抛锚，我要过河
Don't anchor the boat, I need to cross the river!
阁下，水位现在太高了
My Lord, the water levels have risen alarmingly.
这种天气出去我会损失惨重的
I'd have to bear huge losses in taking the boat out in this weather!!
这个够了吧
That should suffice.
看来风暴不会减弱 女士，我们回本德尔坎德吧
Looks like the storm won't abate, My Lady. Let's return to Bundelkhand.
看来这次是白跑一趟了
Our coming here has been in vain.
在普钠，他们把我们和 高级妓女放在一起
In Pune, they kept us amongst courtesans...
在这里又让我们住在河对岸 在这片废墟里
And here in the capital, across the river, amongst these ruins!
我想想都后怕
It frightens me to think...
你嫁的那个男人根本不知道这个传统
The man whose dagger you wed is unaware of this tradition.
要是他拒绝接受跟你的关系怎么办
What if he refuses to accept your relationship?
让我考验我爱的力量吧
Let me test the power of my love.
你不需要再考验了
You needn't... Anymore!
你在整个宫廷前要求佩什瓦
You had demanded the Peshwa before the whole court...
佩什瓦来了
Here he is!
我必须说
I must say...
你为了一个我根本不知道的婚姻 牺牲了一切
You have sacrificed everything over a marriage I was not even aware of!
是什么导致了你的疯狂？
What justifies this madness?
爱
Love...
和汹涌的河水战斗
That battles stormy waters.
是爱，不向任何人低头
Love, that bows down before no one.
是爱，爱它所爱之人胜过一切
Love, that worships its beloved above all else.
这个社会永远不会接受你
This society will never accept you!
爱我就像行走在热灰之上
Loving me will be like walking on hot embers.
我接受
I accept.
我妻子的名字是喀什
My wife's name is Kashi.
她会永远是我的正妻
She will always be my first wife.
我绝不会只属于你
I can never belong only to you.
我接受
I accept.
继续顽固的把我的名字和你 绑在一起只会给你带来羞辱
insisting on adding my name to yours will bring you nothing but shame.
我接受
I accept.
以大地之火，天空和我的名义 我接受你成为我的妻子
By the fire of the earth, the sky and my being, I take you to be my wife.
即使社会抛弃我们，世界也会 永远记得我们是一体的
Even if this society shuns us, the world will always remember us as one...
巴拉吉 玛斯塔妮
Bajirao Mastani.
在安排跟尼扎姆的会面吗
Mapping out your meeting with the Nizam?
走的时候记得戴上
Ensure you wear this when you go.
巴拉吉，这枚戒指让我们付出了 很高的代价
Bajirao, this ring has cost us dearly.
我们不得不以双倍价格把它赎回
We have paid for it twice.
先是找珠宝商，再去找船夫才买到
First to the jeweler and then to the boatman.
阁下，看来毒蛇准备好攻击我们了
My Lord, the snake seems prepared to strike us.
尼扎姆带了两万士兵来
The Nizam comes with twenty-thousand soldiers.
我们寡不敌众
We are heavily outnumbered.
但他不知道
But he doesn't know that.
并非所有战斗都是靠武器来打
Not all battles are fought with weapons...
有时候有敏锐的头脑就足够了
Sometimes a sharp mind is enough.
欢迎，巴拉吉王
Welcome, King Bajirao!
请坐
Have a seat!
日安
Namaste!
你错怪我的忠诚了，我只是 夏胡王谦卑的仆从
You mistake me for royalty when I am but a humble servant to King Shahu.
也许吧...但大家都知道 你才是国家幕后的主脑
Perhaps... But it is well known, you are the mind that runs the empire.
果子露？
Some sherbet?
谢谢
Thank you.
我对你要说的话非常感兴趣
I am more interested in your sweet talk.
我经常告诉马拉地国的人
I often tell people that in the Maratha empire...
能排在伟大的希瓦吉王和 山布王之后的
After the great King Shivaji and King Shambhu...
只有巴拉吉，其他的都是蠢货
There is only Bajirao... Rest are all fools!
我也认为尼扎姆是南方 最强大的力量
I'm also of the opinion that Nizam is the strongest in all of South...
其他的都软弱无能
Rest are all weak and meek!
很了不起，你的舌头 像你的剑一样锋利
I'm impressed... Your tongue is as sharp as your sword.
你的目的像你的眼神已让锐利
And your intentions are as shrewd as your eyes.
我的目的就是抓住你
My intention is to capture you.
在普钠即使是最小的孩子也知道这点
Even the youngest child in Pune knows that.
但你却自愿来这里成为人质
Yet here you are a willing hostage.
我已经发誓，如果你违背 这次会面的目的就必定展开报复
I am under oath to retaliate if you breach the terms of this meeting.
你这是在我的屋檐下威胁我吗
Are you threatening me under my own roof?
这是提醒，不是威胁
Cautioning, not threatening...
走错一步，你的王国就会陷入火海
One wrong turn and your kingdom will burn.
抓住他
Arrest him!
我说了，抓住他
I said, arrest him!
你居然命令我自己的人抓住我 真是让我吃惊
I'm amazed you would order my own men to capture me!
你派去押送我来的人 似乎更喜欢我们那的居住环境
The men you sent to escort me here preferred our living quarters.
于是决定住下了
They decided to stay back.
佩什瓦，你别忘了...
Peshwa, do not forget...
你2万人的军队
That your army of 20,000 men...
马匹，大象都在外面戒备
Horses and elephants, stands guard outside.
但你不知道的是，4万 马拉地士兵就站在他们背后
But what you do not know is that 40,000 Maratha soldiers stand behind them...
等着我的命令准备消灭你
Awaiting my signal to decimate you.
你想要什么？
What do you want?
整个印度
All of India.
但现在，我要你闭嘴
But for now, your silence.
在我向德里进军的时候 你什么话都别说
When I march on Delhi, you will not utter a word.
我接受
I accept.
第二
Secondly...
你要把所有获得的马拉地财产 都还给我们的国王
You shall return all captured Maratha estates to our King.
我接受
I accept.
第三
And thirdly...
在我张开双臂欢迎你的时候
When I welcome you with open arms,..
你要忘掉过去所有的仇恨 接受我的友谊
..you shall forget past animosity and accept my friendship.
来吧
Here!
让鼓声响起来
Let the drums roll...
胜利是我们的
Victory is ours!
我们无敌的战士
"We unbeatable warriors..."
碾碎了敌人
Have crushed the enemy!
胜利的火光在闪耀
The sparks of victory are ablaze.
我们的心充满荣耀
Our hearts are overflowing with pride.
连夜空也充满彩虹
Even the night sky is full of rainbows!
我们的营地活力四射
Our camp is bursting with energy!
我们的庆祝无人能及
Our celebration knows no bounds.
这份胜利
This victory...
我们的胜利
Our victory...
这份胜利只属于我们
This victory of ours is like no other!
母亲
Mother!
巴拉吉的消息
Bajirao's message!
上面说什么，池马基
What does it say, Chimaji?
他跟尼扎姆的会面
His meeting with the Nizam...
成功了
was successful!
赞美神
Praise the Lord!
别哭了，喀什
Stop crying, Kashi!
自从她走进这家门之后 我儿子还没失败过
My son has not seen defeat since she walked into this house.
你还没出生的孩子将来注定 要干大事，喀什
Your unborn child is destined for great things too, Kashi.
母亲，应该为婆罗门 举办一场盛宴来庆祝
Mother, there should be a feast for the Brahmins to celebrate!
同意
Agreed.
送请柬给克利须那·巴特
Send out an invitation to Krishna Bhatt...
今天下午我们要宴请婆罗门
That we shall host the Brahmins this afternoon.
开始准备吧
Start the preparations!
池马基
Chimaji...
也给玛斯塔妮送消息去
Send a message to Mastani as well.
开斋节快乐，到这新家来了 我的女士，我的礼物在哪？
Eid Mubarak in this new house, My Lady! Where is my gift?
那是什么？
What's there?
佩什瓦好像叫了我的名字
I thought the Peshwa called my name.
那怎么可能，我的女士
How is that possible, My Lady!
他会先去沙尼瓦瓦达宫 庆祝对尼扎姆的胜利
He will first go to Shaniwar Wada to celebrate his victory over the Nizam.
玛斯塔妮公主
Mastani Saheba!
这是什么，巴拉吉
What is this Bajirao!
这是你爱情的力量，玛斯塔妮
The power of your love Mastani!
祝你胜利
I wish you on your victory.
祝你开斋节快乐
And I wish you a happy Eid.
你的脸上有光芒，玛斯塔妮
Your face is glowing Mastani.
因为你回来了
Because you have returned.
就像日出前天空的光芒
It's like the glow in the sky, just before sunrise...
我们要为未出生的孩子想个名字了
We'll have to think of a name for our to-be born child!
公主
My Lady!
有佩什瓦母亲给你的消息
There's a message for you from the Peshwa's mother...
是什么？
What is it?
今晚为了庆祝佩什瓦的胜利 将会举办庆典
There shall be a celebration tonight in honour of the Peshwa's victory...
因此玛斯塔妮要受命献上她的舞蹈
On this occasion, Mastani is ordered to present her dance...
女主人，食物已经备好 婆罗门都在等...
Your Ladyship, the food is sewed and the Brahmins are waiting...
为什么佩什瓦没来？
Why is the Peshwa not here?
他正在路上，请开始吧
He is on his way, please begin the feast.
但没有主持人我们要怎么开始？
But how can we begin without the host?
女主人
My Lady!
消息送到了吗
Did you send the message?
是的，但是...
Yes, but...
但是什么？
But what?
玛斯塔妮已经不再是宫廷舞者了
Mastani Saheba will no longer perform as a court dancer.
谁说的？
Says who?
玛斯塔妮吗？
Mastani?
不，女主人，是佩什瓦
No, My Lady... The Peshwa.
他还说他会在开斋节庆典之后回来
He also said that he shall return after the Eid feast...
不用等他
You need not wait for him.
神啊
Dear God...
克里希纳吉
Krishnaji...
我们不能再在这房子里进食了
We cannot eat in this house anymore!!
克利须那·巴特，你这么做 是对佩什瓦的不敬
Krishna Bhatt, you disrespect the Peshwa by doing so!
佩什瓦就没有对我们不敬吗
And hasn't the Peshwa disrespected us?
清真寺一样有庆典举行
Charity is doled out at mosques as well.
我们走
Let's go!
欢迎回家，巴拉吉
Welcome home, Bajirao.
恭喜你战胜了尼扎姆
Congratulations on your win over the Nizam.
也恭喜你
I wish you the same.
长命百岁
Live long!
请原谅我迟到了
Forgive me, I am late.
你在科什特鲁德宫庆祝开斋节的时候
While you were celebrating Eid at Kothrud Palace...
婆罗门人一口东西没吃就离开了
The Brahmins left without eating a morsel.
没事，明天我们可以再请他们回来 再庆祝一次
Never mind, we can invite them back tomorrow and celebrate twice over.
为什么要两次？
Why twice?
玛斯塔妮将要成为我孩子的母亲了
Mastani is about to become the mother of my child.
要是婆罗门人是因为你选择和她 一起庆祝开斋节而离开的
If the Brahmins walked out because you chose to celebrate Eid with her...
他们听到这个消息时会是 什么反应，巴拉吉
What'll they do when this news gets out, Bajirao?
母亲
Mother...
别打断我
Don't interrupt me!
我建议别告诉喀什
I suggest, we don't tell Kashi.
有什么好隐瞒的，母亲
What is there to hide mother?
事实就是如此
The truth is, what it is!
喀什
Kashi...
我到处找你都找不到 原来你在这
I have been looking for you all over and here you are.
我在赏月
I was looking at the moon...
我想告诉你一件很重要的事
I want to tell you something important.
你已经吃过饭了吗
That you have already eaten.
这是你的烤饼
Here's your paan.
不，不是这个
No, that's not it.
喀什，还有别人...
Kashi, there's someone else...
那么传言是真的
So the rumors are true.
什么传言
What rumors?
佩什瓦被恶魔的眼睛迷惑
That the Peshwa's caught the evil eye.
别管那些谣言 我从来不相信那套迷信
Never mind the rumors... I don't believe in superstitions.
但我相信
But I do...
给
Here...
亲爱的玛斯塔妮
Dear Mastani...
在战场上战斗要远比为了保持 与你的关系而战更简单
Fighting in the battlefield is far easier than fighting to keep your relationships intact.
我的内心无时无刻不在希望与你在一起
My heart wishes to be with you every single moment.
但我不把我们的关系告诉喀什 我就不能见你
But I cannot meet you till I, myself, don't inform Kashi of our relationship.
喀什不仅是我的正房妻子 也是我的朋友和知己
Kashi is not just my first wife... She is my friend and confidant too.
在那之前，请你保重
Until then, please take care of yourself.
久姆里
Jhumri...
公主
My Lady!
你带来了什么消息，维·辛格？
What news have you brought, Veer Singh?
我今天没能把你的消息传达给佩什瓦
I couldn't deliver your message to the Peshwa even today...
听说他病得非常重 无法见任何人
News is that he is very ill and unable to meet anyone.
马上备轿，我这就去见他
Get the palanquin ready. I shall go to meet him right away.
这消息可能是假的，公主
This news could be false, My Lady...
也可能是真的
It could be true!
这时候去沙尼瓦瓦达宫 可能对你有危险
Going to Shaniwar Wada at this hour could be dangerous for you.
马帕特·劳
Mahipat Rao...
维·辛格，你在这干什么
Veer Singh, what are you doing here?
玛斯塔妮公主来见佩什瓦了
Mastani Saheba is here to meet the Peshwa.
他在书房里
He is in his office.
是谁？
Who is there?
阿巴吉·潘的儿媳
Ambaji Panth's daughter-in-law.
沙鲁白
Shalubai!
是
Yes.
去看看是谁
See who that is.
是
Yes.
沙鲁白，是谁？
Shalubai... Who is it?
是阿巴吉·潘的儿媳
It is Ambaji Panth's daughter-in-law.
那乔皮卡柏的轿子在哪？ 他们是一起离开的
So where is Gopikabai's palanquin... They had left together.
我去问问？
Shall I find out?
不，我亲自去
No, I'll go myself.
玛斯塔妮公主，请在镜宫前等候
Mastani Saheba, please wait at the Palace of Mirrors...
我去通知佩什瓦
I shall inform the Peshwa.
玛斯塔妮，是什么让你在 这个时候前来
Mastani, what brings you here at this hour?
巴拉吉
Bajirao.
你不该冒生命危险来这里
You shouldn't have risked your life by coming here.
只要能和你在一起，什么风险都无所谓
There's no bigger risk to my life than spending a moment without you.
你没收到我的信
You never got my letter...
周围的城墙太高了，我翻越不了
These fort walls have become too high to scale.
但你却来了这里
Yet here you are, Mastani.
果然没有任何东西能阻挡爱
It's true that nothing can come in the way of love.
喀什公主的轿子来了
Lady Kashi's palanquin is here...
婴儿床送到她那了吗
Has the crib reached her quarters?
神啊，我疏忽了
Dear God! It slipped my mind! I'll check right away.
佩什瓦随时可能到达
The Peshwa must be arriving any minute now!
公主
My Lady...
我像你一直以来那样站在这欢迎你
I stand to welcome you like you always do...
你从母亲子宫中降生
You have brought back light to this lifeless".
为这个了无生机的宫殿带来了光明
..palace by returning from your maternal home.
让我看看我们最年轻的战士
Let me see our youngest warrior!
是个男孩
N's a boy!
给，给
Here, Here!
力气真大
Strong lad!
你会成为比巴拉吉更强大的战士
You will be a warrior even greater than Bajirao.
你有跟母亲一样美丽的眼睛
You have your mother's beautiful eyes...
站住
Stop!
让我进去
Let me in!
不行
You cannot!
我必须见阁下
I must meet My Lord!
现在不可能
It is not possible at this hour.
大人
My Lord!
快点，大人，玛斯塔妮公主非常痛苦
Make haste My Lord, Mastani Saheba is in great pain.
没有哪个产婆或是医生愿意帮她接生
No midwife or doctor is willing to attend to her.
要是...
What if-
她会没事的
She will be fine.
一只雌虎不需要医生或是产婆
A tigress needs no doctors or midwives...
对不对，池马基
Isn't it Chimaji?
公主确实受了很多苦，大人 而且没人愿意帮忙
My Lady is truly suffering, Sir... And no one is ready to help!
玛斯塔妮，深呼吸
Mastani, breathe...
生下一名战士从来不简单
Giving birth to a warrior is never easy.
看
Look!
克利须那
Krishna.
我从北方归来
Upon my return from the north,..
我将组织一场为我两个儿子 举办的命名仪式 ..I’ll organise a naming ceremony for both my sons.
不要再玩弄我们的耐心
Don't toy with our patience anymore...
碧秀姑妈，告诉我们 你选的名字
Aunt Bhiu, tell us what name you have chosen.
告诉我们
Tell us.
是什么？
Well, what will it be?
拉古纳特
Raghunath!
等巴拉吉回来，听到这个名字 他会很高兴的
When Bajirao is back, he will be happy to hear the name.
我的拉古巴
My Raghoba.
多可爱的名字啊，公主
What a lovely name, My Lady.
欢迎，玛斯塔妮
Welcome, Mastani.
欢迎
Welcome!
你来得正是时候
You have come at an opportune moment.
你能来我太高兴了
Glad you could come.
母亲
Mother...
一个人怎么才能失去所有自尊
How can someone lose all shame..
还不断回到你的门口被你羞辱
..and keep returning to your doorstep to be insulted?
在你自己的家门口 究竟还要如何攻击他人？
What offence can come at your own doorstep?
不准冒犯你自己的亲人
No insult can come by your own people.
我是来祝福巴拉吉的孩子的
I am here to bless Bajirao's child.
你却是来祝福他们的关系的吗 还是来祈求接受的？
Are you here to bless relations or to beg acceptance?
巴拉吉无法出席，所以我是 替他带着礼物来的
I am here with gifts on Bajirao's behalf in his absence.
如果你想让我们接受你
If you had to please your way into our family...
那你应该穿上红色衣服 而不是这绿色的毒药
Then you should've got saffron clothes and not this green colored poison.
人们把宗教和颜色联系在一起 但颜色是不分宗教的
People have associated each religion with color, but colour has no religion...
只有心变黑了，你才会开始 区分这些背景
It is when the heart turns black that you start differentiating on such grounds.
算了，池马基
Leave it, Chimaji...
她已经忘记了
She has forgotten the difference..
杜尔迦和达加的区别
..between durga(A HINDU GODDESS) and dargah(MUSLIM SHRINE).
也许是你忘了，清真寺的神像 常常装饰着绿色
Perhaps you forget that idols in temples are often adorned in green...
而红床单则被盖在苏非派的坟墓上
And saffron sheets cover the purest Sufi tombs.
这时候人们还考虑颜色和宗教吗？
Where is the thought of colour and religion then?
巴拉吉只是牵牵你的手 你的舌头就开始像利剑一样伤人了
Bajirao merely holds your hand and your tongue begins to cut like a sword.
一个战士的本能就是当被攻击时 必定拔剑反击
A warrior's instinct is to reach for her sword even when struck by a pebble.
克利须那·巴特
Krishna Bhatt...
今年在我们为亡者祈祷时 也加入给她的祷告
This year when we pray for the deceased, add a prayer for her too...
这样她在我们心里就是死人了
So that she is dead for us.
现在离开
Leave us now!
那些祷告不是为陌生人做的，母亲
Those prayers are not for strangers, Mother...
我很高兴你还把我当自己人
I'm grateful you thought of me as your own.
欢迎
Welcome!
我想让你组织我儿子的命名仪式
I want you to organise my son's naming ceremony.
那已经完成了，大人 他已经被赐予了出生星盘
That's already been done, My Lord. He has a blessed birth chart.
不，不是拉古纳特 我说的是我的另一个儿子，克利须那
No, not Raghunath... I am talking about my other son, Krishna.
他也是我的儿子
He is my son too.
陛下，传统不允许我们这么做
My Lord, traditions do not permit that.
为什么？
Why?
按照传统，儿子应该继承父亲的宗教
As per our tradition, a son inherits his father's religion...
不是那样吗
Isn't that right?
你怎么会犯这种错误，大人
How can you be wrong, My Lord.
但孩子的父母依照印度教律法结合
But it is imperative for the child's parents to be...
是必须的
married under the Hindu law.
我会按照印度教律法娶玛斯塔妮
I shall marry Mastani as per the Hindu law.
开始准备吧
Begin the preparations.
恐怕那不可能了
I'm afraid it still won't be possible.
为什么？
Why not?
克利须那是在婚姻之外生下的孩子 而他将永远都是...
Krishna was born out of wedlock and he shall always remain...
私生子
illegitimate!
我说的对吗？
Am I right?
对，对
Yes, yes...
你想的是私生子，克利须那·巴特
Your thinking is illegitimate, Krishna Bhatt.
宗教胜过一切，大人，甚至胜过你
Religion is bigger than anything, My Lord... Even you!
我们不能亵渎神明
We cannot be a part of such blasphemy!
你的想法对我来说无所谓
Your thoughts do not matter to me.
如果你不能让他遵从我的信仰
If you cannot initiate him into my faith...
那他就随他母亲的宗教
Then he shall follow his mother's.
从今天开始他不再叫克利须那 而是沙姆谢尔阁下
And from today he will not be called Krishna, but Shamsher Bahadur!
退下
Leave.
我们要加快收税
We need to speed up tax collections.
把消息传达给收税人
Send a message to the collectors.
为什么要惊扰这份美
Why are these sweets being distributed?
怎么回事
What is the occasion?
这些是谁的
Who are these from?
我的
These are from me.
请收下
Please have.
池马基，这是你最喜欢的
Chimaji, it's your favourite.
怎么了，兄弟
What is the occasion, brother?
我为克利须那举行了命名仪式 更改了他的名字
I had a naming ceremony for Krishna and changed his name.
你给他取了什么名字，大人
And what have you named him, My Lord?
沙姆谢尔阁下
Shamsher Bahadur.
佩什瓦中穆斯林派系的名字
The name of Peshwa's Muslim lineage.
你们都可以退下了
You all may leave.
潘，看看他的脸
Panth, look at his face!
念
Read it.
佩什瓦下令将两处房产作为礼物 送给玛斯塔妮·巴拉吉·巴拉德
The Peshwa decrees two estates to be gifted to Mastani Bajirao Ballad.
不可能，巴拉吉
Impossible, Bajirao!
我们不能容忍这样的行为
We do not entertain such practices.
从今天开始，我们会的
From this day on, we shall.
你说呢，潘
What say, Panth?
我无法理解，你还在这里 她为什么需要这些房屋
I fail to understand, why does she need estates when you are here?
你看不出来吗，潘
Don't you see, Panth?
如果他们能在我还活着时 把她赶出我的家门...
If they can throw her out of my house while I'm alive...
想象一下我离开之后 他们会如何威胁她
Imagine how they'd treat her when I'm gone.
你得保护所爱之人的自由
You have to safeguard the future of your loved ones.
今天给的是房子 明天你就会把整个佩什瓦王国给她
Today it's an estate, tomorrow you'll gift her the entire Peshwa kingdom.
你不能因为一时兴起就送出自己的国土
You cannot gift away territory at whim.
但你能因为一时兴起 就把一个女人送进妓院吗？
But you can put up a woman in a brothel at whim?
那就是我所知道的
That is my understanding.
我也清楚了
Make me understand as well.
好马配好鞍...
A dagger deserves a sheath...
妻子理应有个家
A wife deserves a home...
而情妇只能住小屋
<i>And</i> a <i>mistress deserves</i> a <i>hovel!</i>
你完全做错了，大人
You missed your aim, My Lord.
不...我们的关系成为了阻碍
No... Our relationship came in the way.
所以我说...
That's why I say...
你必须斩断一切 已经成为阻碍的关系
You must end all relations that become a hindrance.
有时候一些关系 能要了你的命
Sometimes your relations themselves finish you.
给旨意盖印
Seal the orders!
巴拉吉和他兄弟今天 在朝堂上大打出手
Bajirao fought with his brother today in front of the entire court...
为了那个女人放弃了 自己尊贵的身份
stripping his relationship of dignity, all for that mistress.
这是不对的
It's wrong!
我已经无法分清谁是谁非了
I do not understand right or wrong anymore mother.
我这辈子都生活在他的阴影中...
I lived my entire life as his shadow...
有一天他就那样陷入黑暗
And one day he just walked into darkness...
从没想过要从阴暗中走出来
Not once thinking that this shadow will fade away.
没有人比我更了解你的痛苦
No one can understand your pain like me...
这个家族中女人的地位 就像芒果园一样灿烂...
The status of the lady of this house may be as grand as a mango orchard...
人人都想得到芒果...
Whose fruit is longed for by all...
但是为了得到芒果 就得用石头去砸芒果树
But to acquire the fruit, one must stone the trees...
而那恰恰就是芒果树的命运
And that is the orchard's destiny.
喀什...
Kashi...
我们应该把旗帜缝成绿色 好迎合那个女人的喜好
We should've sewn the flag green, to the mistress's liking!
主啊
Oh Lord!
(CHANTS)
来吧，克利须那·巴特，你好，妈妈
Come, Krishna Bhatt. Hello, Mother.
你怎么知道我们来了，大人？
How did you know, My Lord?
勇士必须时刻保持警惕
A warrior must always be alert.
敌人随时可能出击
Enemy can strike at any moment.
拉加夫，向你祖母问好
Raghav, greet your grandmother.
沙姆谢尔，你也是
Shamsher, you too.
克利须那·巴特想知道你何时 进行忏悔祷告
Krishna Bhatt wanted to know, when you will perform the repentance prayers.
忏悔？
Repentance?
你以前每年都做的...
You used to perform it every year...
用以慰藉烈士的亡魂
For the gratification of martyrs' souls.
现在你已经两年没做祷告了
You haven't performed it in two years.
是的，我不会再做了
Yes, and it won't happen again.
你不想成为婆罗门人？
You are refusing it being a Brahmin?
出身让我成为婆罗门人 但是命运让我成为战士
I am Brahmin only by birth, but a warrior by destiny.
这是用以净化我们灵魂的 强制性的仪式
This ritual is mandatory for the purification of our soul.
那好，那就净化我们的灵魂吧...
Alright, let's purify our souls...
我要带玛斯塔妮去沙尼瓦瓦达宫 让她成为我的合法妻子...
I shall bring Mastani to Shaniwar Wada and give her the rights of being my wife...
那是我唯一的赎罪之法
That can be my only atonement.
有你这样的儿子让我很骄傲
I am proud to have a son like you...
你知道该如何尊重一个女人
Who knows how to respect a woman...
但是你的要求是不可能实现的
But what you ask for is impossible.
绝不可能，我的儿子
Never, my son!
我会选一个黄道吉日...
On Saptami (AUSPICIOUS DAY)...
将玛斯塔妮带去沙尼瓦瓦达宫
I shall bring Mastani to Shaniwar Wada.
如若发生此事，婆罗门 就会驱逐整个佩什瓦部族
The Brahmins shall ostracize the entire Peshwa clan if that were to happen.
欢迎回家...
Welcome home...
大家都应该知道玛斯塔妮宫殿
lt shall be known to all as Mastani Mahal.
潘...
Panth...
哥哥...
Brother...
池马基...
Chimaji....
看来大家都没来欢迎你
Everyone seems to be welcoming you with their absence!
池马基和阿巴吉外出巡视领地去了
Chimaji and Ambaji have gone out to inspect lands.
母亲去朝圣了
Mother has gone on a pilgrimage.
所以，作为这里的女主人
So as the lady of this house...
我欢迎你和你的客人
I welcome you and your guest.
来吧
Come.
不要碰我的脚
Don't touch my feet! (A HINDU TRADITION OF GIVING BLESSINGS)
感谢你维护我的荣誉，我的夫人
Thank you for keeping my honour, My Lady.
这让我感到轻松
It lightens my mind.
别忘了，我的大人
Don't forget My Lord...
这欢迎只是表面的 并非发自内心
This welcome stops at the threshold, it doesn't extend to the heart.
纳纳，你何时到的？
Nana! When did you arrive?
你没从首都送消息来
You didn't write or send a message from the capital.
如果我知道你要来 就会盛装欢迎您
Had I known you were coming, I would've welcomed you in style.
您好
Namaste.
祝福你
Stay blessed!
你变得这么高了
You've grown so tall.
你开始长胡子了
Your moustache has started showing too.
希望你从国王身边 学会了政治
I hope you are learning politics from the king.
是的
Yes.
我也希望你学会了 一些政治，母亲
I wish you learnt some politics as well, Mother.
什么意思？
Meaning?
你爱上的这个男人配不上你
The man for whom you hold this flame, doesn't deserve it.
你做什么？
What have you done?
你做了什么，纳纳？
What did you do, Nana?
知道你在评论谁吗？
Do you know who you are talking about?
是的，妈妈
Yes, Mother.
是那个从普纳到首都 都在被人议论的男人
The man who is the talk of every town from Pune to the capital...
他用本德尔坎德的火炬 烧毁了自己的家园
For burning his own home with Bundelkhand's torch.
而你却在这为他祈祷
Yet you sit here praying for him!
纳纳
Nana!
不要太担心我，我的儿子
Don't worry about me so much, my son.
夫人
My Lady!
希瓦·巴特，你吓坏我了
Shiva Bhatt, you startled me!
祷告就要开始了
The prayers are about to start.
夫人，今晚会发生大灾难
My Lady, a grave disaster is about to happen tonight.
什么灾难？
What disaster?
有人打算在祈祷时袭击玛斯塔妮宫殿
While we pray, Mastani Mahal will be attacked.
有人想刺杀她 请你尽力救她
She will be murdered. Please save her if you can!
上帝保佑
Hail Lord Ganesha (HINDU GOD OF OBSTACLES).
你要如何抵偿这罪过，克利须那·巴特？
How shall you atone for this crime, Krishna Bhatt?
有何证据证明克利须那·巴特 杀害了希瓦·巴特？
What proof exists that Krishna Bhatt has murdered Shiva Bhatt?
母亲...
Mother...
你要如何抵偿这罪过？
How shall you atone for this crime?
接受何种惩罚？
What atonement, what punishment?
任何违背教义的人都将 有如此下场
Whoever opposes religion will meet such an end.
算你的情人运气好 不然她早已被大卸八块了
It was your mistress's good fortune, else she would've been cut to pieces as well.
大人，您母亲到了
My Lord, your mother is here.
为何把我们当犯人一样召唤到此？
Why have we been summoned like criminals, despite sharing the same roof?
当人们心中产生了隔阂 就无法同住一屋了
When walls come up between hearts, they no longer hold a house together.
是的，我们知道
Yes, we get it!
为什么召唤我们？ 我们所犯何罪？
Why have you summoned us? What's our crime?
克利须那·巴特
Krishna Bhatt!
包庇罪犯就是你的罪行
Protecting a criminal is your crime.
你怎敢这样对妈妈说话？
How dare you talk to mother in this manner!
那你呢？
And you?
你怎敢用这样的口气对佩什瓦 家的人说话
How dare you talk to the Peshwa in this manner.
大人
My Lord!
让他知道，我不是每次都会失手
Remind him, I won't miss my aim every time.
巴拉吉，不是你的原因...
Bajirao, this isn't you...
而是因为本德尔坎德的礼物 她迷失了你的心智
But the influence of Bundelkhand's gift. She has gotten to your head.
她也迷失了你的心智
Bundelkhand's gifts are on your head too...
你头上的宝石，脖子上的珍珠 都是本德尔坎德的礼物
These jewels on your head, around your neck; are all Bundelkhand's gifts...
你无法接受这些礼物？
You can't accept these gifts?
那就抛弃它们
Then take them off!
本德尔坎德的礼物可以接受 但是不能接受他们的女人
Bundelkhand's gifts are accepted, not their daughter.
玛斯塔妮可以成为我的情人 但无法成为我的妻子
Mastani as my mistress is accepted, not as my wife...
但你要记住，巴拉吉 对于玛斯塔妮的爱是无条件的
But remember mother, Bajirao's love for Mastani is unconditional.
你为何这么怨恨她，母亲？
Where do you find such hatred for her, mother?
佩什瓦的纯正血统不能 受到玷污，就是因为这个
Peshwa blood cannot be adulterated by an outsider, it's that simple!
就是因那个？
That's been done... Now?
是的
That's what!
你和穆斯林人开战 却爱上了他们中的一员？
You fight Muslims and yet fell in love with one of them?
我是和莫卧儿帝国开战 而不是和他们的宗教开战
I fight the Mughal dynasty, not their religion.
我最后请求你一次
I ask you one last time...
巴拉吉继续留在佩什瓦家族的 唯一条件是你们接受玛斯塔妮...
Bajirao shall remain Peshwa only if Mastani is accepted...
同意吗？
Agreed?
不同意
No.
那是你的了
It's yours!
巴拉吉
Bajirao.
喀什
Kashi!
我一直在找你 没想到在这见到你
I've been looking for you all over. I've wished everyone except you.
你去哪？
Where are you going?
我马上回来
I'll be back soon.
但是你要去哪？
But where are you going?
玛斯塔妮宫殿
Mastani Mahal
见到你真开心，姐姐
I'm happy to see you, sister.
要叫夫人...不是姐姐
My Lady'... Not sister.
我是佩什瓦家的合法妻子
I'm the Peshwa's legally wedded wife.
喀什·巴拉吉·巴拉德
Kashi Bajirao Ballad.
我们已经有了很久的交情
We've been related for years -
什么交情？
What relation?
说不出来？
Say?
和你结婚的男人也是我的丈夫
The man you are married to, is my husband as well.
也许是吧
Maybe so.
但是据我所知 当一个已婚的男人...
But as far as I know, when a married man..
娶了另一个妻子 那她就是妃子
..takes another wife, she's known as a concubine...
这个词太严重了...
It is such a heavy word...
有个更简单的词语...
There is a simpler term for it...
情妇
Mistress.
你说出这样嘲弄的话是不合适的
Such mockery is unbecoming of you.
是吗
Really!
但有谁比你更了解什么是嘲弄
But who understands mockery better than you!
不顾本德尔坎德的人民
Leaving your people behind in Bundelkhand..
为了一个男人一路跑来普纳...
..to run after a man all the way to Pune...
玛斯塔妮公主，这才是笑话
That, Mastani Saheba, is mockery.
没良心还有什么关系？
Do matters of the heart have no meaning?
你说的是何意思？
What heart do you talk of?
在不同人身上换来换去的心
A heart that flitters from one to another?
在这里可是容不下它的
There is no place for such purposeless matters...
那么你的到来肯定有所企图
Then your visit must have purpose too.
当然了
Of course.
今天是个节日
We have a festival today.
已婚女人在这一天聚集到一起 为祈求丈夫的长寿而庆祝 Married women come together to celebrate this day for their husbands‘ long lives...
她们用朱砂装饰额头
They adorn their foreheads with vermilion.
我不能再贬低你了
I can't demean you any further...
但你将会在这里面对不少挑衅
But you will have to face a lot of humiliation here...
不要放在心上
Don't take it to heart.
劳有你才能幸福 而我有他才能幸福
Rao's happiness lies with you and mine with his...
那就是我的企图
That's my purpose.
来吧，点上
Here, put.
这就是他握住的手...
This is the hand he holds...
比起我的手，他宁愿握剑
He prefers holding his sword to my hand...
但是他认为你的手比 任何宝剑都珍贵
But he holds your hand dearer than any sword.
他握着我的手 但也不愿松开你的手
He has held my hand without letting go of yours...
他是爱我，但也无法舍弃你
He has loved me, but not broken ties with you.
我也许是他的灵感来源 但你是他的力量之源
He may call me his inspiration, but you remain his strength...
他对你的爱并没有减少
His love for you has not withered.
或许我是非法的 但是你的到来...
I may be illegitimate, but your coming here..
已经确认了我的存在
..has validated my presence amongst you all.
给...
Here...
这纱丽很适合你
This sari will look good on you.
我先走了
I'll take your leave.
让我们一起庆祝婚姻的神圣
Let us celebrate the sanctity of marriage.
让我们一起为丈夫的长寿祈祷 Let us pray for our husbands‘ long lives.
她来了，像是爱神
Here she comes, looking like Radha.
我天真无辜的爱人... 她像一轮满月般来到我门前
My love's innocent beloved... She appears at my door, like a full moon.
今天我们一起起舞
Today on this occasion, together we shall dance...
你的爱让我痛苦 就像穿过心脏的匕首
Your love has caused me pain, like a dagger through my heart.
你可以随意评价我 但我只是迷失在爱情中的灵魂
You may accuse me of anything, but I'm just a soul lost in love.
也许那是我们的命运...
Maybe that's our destiny...
爱上一个无法完全 属于自己的男人
To love a man who can never belong completely to either one of us.
大人，尼扎姆的儿子纳西贾 已经起兵反对我们
My Lord, Nizam's son, Nasirjung has revolted against us.
如何？
So?
他已经穿过戈达尔河 正往斯哈赫加尔进发
He has crossed the river Godavri and is approaching Shahgarh.
那又如何？
So?
看来殿下沉醉了
It appears My Lord is intoxicated.
是吗？
So?
谁能不沉醉呢？
Who is not?
大家都沉醉了
Everyone is intoxicated.
克利须那·巴特沉醉在 财富，信仰，权利和美色之间
By wealth, religion, power... Pratinidhi, Krishna Bhatt are all intoxicated.
我也一样...
So am I...
我沉浸在爱情之中
I am intoxicated by love!
殿下，你站的不稳
You are unsteady, My Lord!
也许我脚站不稳 但是我的剑术依然很稳健
My feet may be unsteady but my grip is firm.
马尔哈·劳，怎么样？
What say, Malhar Rao?
看啊
Look!
所以我们需要你 为我们赢得胜利，佩什瓦
That is why we need you to win this battle for us, Peshwa.
我已经不是佩什瓦了
I am no longer the Peshwa!
但你是我们的指挥官
But you are our Commander.
我也不再是指挥官了
I am not a Commander either.
你第一次学骑马的时候 我们随行在你身边
When you first learnt to ride, we ran alongside your horse.
我们都为你捏了一把汗
We put in as much sweat as your steed.
马尔哈·劳为你而战 为了你的荣耀忍受伤痛
Malhar Rao fought battles beside you, suffered injuries to uphold your honour.
土可奇为了照顾你不惜受伤
Tukoji nursed you despite being wounded himself.
指挥官是不能犹豫的，殿下
Commanders aren't made overnight, My Lord!
敌人一旦出现，就必须迎击
And when the enemy stands at our gates, you are abdicating your duties.
巴拉吉的心也许属于玛斯塔妮 但他的生命属于他的祖国...
Bajirao's heart may belong to Mastani, but his life belongs to his homeland...
成千上万的巴拉吉和玛斯塔妮
A thousand Bajiraos and Mastanis will be happily..
将为了又一个马拉地大捷 甘愿做出牺牲
..sacrificed for one more Maratha victory.
放出消息
Let it be known...
巴拉吉将在除夕出发作战
Bajirao will leave for battle on New Year's eve.
赞美我主
Praise the Lord!
现在应该把灯点着，而不是吹灭
It's a day to light lamps, not extinguish them.
你没说要来
You didn't send word of your arrival.
佩什瓦无需向人告知他的计划
The Peshwa doesn't inform of his plans.
你有一阵子没来了
You haven't been here for a while.
四处徘徊的人很容易找到...
Those who wander can be found...
但是在自家院里迷路的人 就很难找到了
But ones who lose themselves within their own house are hard to trace.
好的
OK!
作为这里的第一夫人 你不送我上战场？
As the first lady of this house, won't you see me off to war?
是服装和珠宝让我 成为了这里的夫人
If clothes and jewels alone make me Lady of this house.
(CALLS OUT TO CHAMBERMAID)
拿垫子来
Bring the pooja thaali (A PRAYER PLATE).
来吧，坐下
Here, sit.
我得留你孤单一人，喀什
I have left you alone, Kashi.
我不孤单，殿下
I am never alone, My Lord.
整天都忙于家务琐事
The entire day passes in household chores...
晚上则陪着牧师 听着布道
And evenings are spent with my Raghoba, listening to sermons.
牧师昨天给我们讲了个好故事 过来坐着，我讲给你听
The Priest told us a nice story yesterday... Sit with me, I shall tell you.
牧师说...
The priest was saying...
克利须那大人和他的妻子 鲁克玛尼曾有过对话
Lord Krishna and his wife Rukmani were having a dialogue...
鲁克玛尼说，我也爱着
Rukmani said, I have loved you too...
但我希望我是你的情人 而不是你的妻子
Yet I wish I was your beloved and not your wife.
为什么？
Why?
克利须那大人也问“为何？”
Lord Krishna also asked, 'Why'?
鲁克玛尼说无论婚姻的结合如何紧密
Rukmani said however deep a matrimonial bond may be...
世人记住的只有情人
The world always remembers the beloved.
克利须那万岁，克利须那万岁
Radhe Krishna, Radhe Krishna! (FAMOUS DEVOTIONAL CHANT)
喀什，对我来说 你和玛斯塔妮一样重要
Kashi, you are as dear to me as Mastani.
克利须那大人也说过一样的话
Lord Krishna also said the same.
我从不拿你们两做比较
I have never compared you two.
也许我们两人没有可比性
There can be no comparison between us!
我不想和你说大道理
I didn't perform the Rasa Leela (DIVINE DANCE OF PASSION) with you.
你对于我们的抱怨是应该的
Your complaints against Mastani and I are justified.
熟悉的人之间有抱怨是难免的
What complaints can one have against strangers.
被自己人伤害才是最痛苦的
The wounds inflicted by one's own hurt most.
大人，即使你要我死...
Had you asked for my life, My Lord...
我也会面带微笑的去牺牲
I would have sacrificed it with a smile.
但你剥夺了我的自尊
But you've stripped me of my pride.
我应该开心的接受惩罚 因为我带给了你伤害
I shall happily accept your punishments for the hurt I've caused you.
惩罚？不，我应该给你个好消息
Punishments? No, I shall give you good news.
什么意思？
What do you mean?
你永远不得再踏足我的寝宫
You shall never enter these chambers again.
知道你在说什么吗？
Do you know what you ask for?
我在来这里时就为了 你的幸福立下誓言
I took a vow to keep you happy when I set foot in this house...
我只是想做到它
I'm only trying to uphold it.
给
Here!
赞美我主
Praise the Lord!
该告辞了，玛斯塔妮
It's time to bid farewell, Mastani.
我等你回来
I shall await your return.
当夕阳和月亮一起出现在天空时 我们就能见面
We shall meet when the setting sun and rising moon appear together in the sky.
天空将改变颜色 一切都将沐浴在橙光之中
The sky will change colour, and all will be bathed in an orange glow.
欲望之风将会吹拂 雷云布满整个天空
Winds of desire will blow, And thundering clouds will fill the skies.
干枯的树叶将会低语 不合时宜的雨水将冲刷大地
Dry leaves will murmur and untimely rains will wash the earth.
不会再有宗教的枷锁 或者人情世故拆散我们
There will be no shackles of religion or relationships to tear us apart.
所有这一切将成为 我们心中爱的火焰...
All that will remain will be the fire of love in our hearts...
在那一天，我们将变得不朽
On that day... We will become one for eternity.
你找我吗，祖母？
You called for me, grandmother?
是时候擦除我们的污名 赢回家族的名声了，纳纳
It's time to erase the dishonour brought to our family, Nana.
把玛斯塔妮抓起来
Arrest Mastani.
我们要怎么向佩什瓦交待？
What shall we tell the Peshwa?
别害怕
Don't be scared.
如果事关国家的存亡...
When it comes to protecting the kingdom...
即使是最亲的亲人也可以牺牲
Even the closest relations must be sacrificed.
你像祷文一样在我心中
You are in my heart, like a prayer.
我带着崇拜提起你的名字...
The mention of your name shall be my worship...
巴拉吉殿下 我们已经彻底包围了纳西贾
We have surrounded Nasirjung from all sides, Bajirao.
马尔哈·劳和他的部队在北边...
Malhar Rao is in the north with his troops...
瓦曼·劳和阿巴吉·潘在南边
Vaman Rao and Ambaji Panth are in the south.
我们要如何进攻？
How shall we strategise the attack?
正面进攻
Head-on.
就像生活一样...
Like life does...
你不知道它何时会袭击你
You don't know when it hits you!
殿下
My Lord!
你在这干嘛，维·辛格？
What are you doing here, Veer Singh?
纳纳把玛斯塔妮公主抓起来了
Nana Saheb has arrested Mastani Saheba!
巴拉吉
Bajirao!
跟上巴拉吉
Go with Bajirao.
准备进攻
Prepare for attack!
(WAR CRY)
这是你回到本德尔坎德最后的机会
It's your last chance to return to Bundelkhand.
如果我打算回去 就不会被抓住
I wouldn't have allowed these shackles if I planned to return.
我对你深恶痛绝，玛斯塔妮
My hatred for you goes beyond its very essence, Mastani.
你只是怨恨我不朽的爱
Your hatred only immortalizes my love, Nana.
把她的孩子带走
Carry her child away!
没必要
No need for that.
巴拉吉的儿子应该自己走出去
Bajirao's son shall walk out on his own feet.
沙姆谢尔阁下
Shamsher Bahadur.
谁是勇士？
Who is a warrior?
他，没有畏惧的人
He, who fears none.
他相信什么？
What is self belief?
胜利的信号
Sign of victory.
害怕什么？
Fear?
失败的恐惧
Another name for defeat.
谁是你的榜样？
Who shall be your ideal?
佩什瓦·巴拉吉·巴拉德
Peshwa Bajirao Ballad.
再见
Goodbye.
再见，妈妈
Goodbye, Mother.
印度只有一名勇士 连续取得了四十场战斗的胜利
There's only one warrior in all of India to have won forty consecutive battles.
就是佩什瓦·巴拉吉
Peshwa Bajirao!
纳西贾投降了...
Nasirjung has surrendered...
这是又一个马拉地大捷
Here's to one more Maratha victory!
也是我的失败
And my loss.
我不明白...
I don't understand...
宣战吧，接下来我要进攻普纳
Declare war... I shall attack Pune next.
我要救出玛斯塔妮
I shall release Mastani.
你要和自己的家人为敌？
You will fight against your own family?
你要因为玛斯塔妮和我们为敌？
You will turn against us for Mastani?
你要把谁杀了？ 母亲，喀什，还是你儿子...
And who will you kill? Mother, Kashi or your son...
巴拉吉...
Bajirao...
我走了
I take your leave.
我们必须确定这次 胜利可以改变他的心意...
We must certify this victory before Nasirjung can change his mind...
我很快回来
I'll be back soon.
请进来，大人
Please come inside, My Lord.
大风会让你的发热加重
This breeze could aggravate your fever.
我在等人
I am waiting for someone...
玛斯塔妮，你没得选择了 说出你最后的愿望
Mastani, you have run out of options, so name your last wish...
你想怎么死？
How would you like to die?
和佩什瓦·巴拉吉一起死
With Peshwa Bajirao!
这病我也没办法
This ailment is beyond my understanding, Sir.
高烧没有减退
The fever shows no sign of subsiding.
是时候联系喀什和妈妈了
It is time to call Kashi and Mother.
和家人一起也许对他的健康有利
Being with family might improve his health.
国王不同意我们的做法，祖母
The king's orders are against us, Grandmother.
你在听吗？
Are you listening?
他说他不能失去 巴拉吉那样的勇士
He says he cannot lose a warrior like Bajirao...
因此我们必须释放玛斯塔妮
And hence we must release Mastani.
我明天要去首都
I shall travel to the capital tomorrow.
我要和国王谈谈
I shall speak to the king.
我明天要去拉维奇迪...
I shall travel to Ravelkhedi tomorrow...
巴拉吉生病了
Bajirao is unwell.
我和他回来之前不会出事
And nothing can happen till I return with him.
你害怕了吗，祖母？
Are you scared, Grandmother?
你们都得对玛斯塔妮行礼
You all may bow down before Mastani...
但我不会
But I shall not!
我不会
I shall not!
看看谁来了，大人
Look who is here, My Lord.
玛斯塔妮
Mastani
沙姆谢尔好吗？
ls Shamsher well?
是的，他很好
Yes, he is.
他在学骑马
He's learning to ride.
喀什呢？
Kashi?
她也很好...
She's well too...
忙着伪装自己的铁石心肠
Busy pretending that her heart has turned to stone.
我需要你阻止它
I need your stamp on this.
再说吧
Later.
这不能等
This can't wait.
什么事这么急？
What is so urgent?
玛斯塔妮的释放命令
Mastani's release orders.
你疯了吗，喀什？
Have you lost your mind, Kashi?
只有她能救巴拉吉
Only she can save Bajirao.
我不能批准
I cannot approve this.
我不能眼睁睁看着巴拉吉死去
I cannot see Bajirao losing himself.
战无不胜的男人就要 死在自己家人手里了
The man who never lost a battle is losing to his own family.
我不能批准
I cannot approve that!
批准吧
Stamp this!
不能让她进佩什瓦家的门
She has no rights in the Peshwa family.
但我愿意...我要求如此
But I do... And I'm demanding it.
以我家族夫人的身份
As the lady of this house.
批准吧
Stamp this.
马上把这个送给纳纳大人
Take this to Nana Saheb right away.
有什么消息？
What is the news from Ravelkhedi?
佩什瓦怎么样了？
How is the Peshwa?
我也在等他的消息
I too await news of him.
在那之前，为他祈祷吧
Until then, pray for him.
(PRAYERS)
上面说什么？
What is the message?
祖母下令释放玛斯塔妮
Grandmother has ordered Mastani's release.
你去哪，巴拉吉？
Where are you going, Bajirao?
看，沙尼瓦瓦达宫着火了
Look, Shaniwar Wada is on fire!
不，不是...
No, it isn't...
巴拉吉，这里不是普纳 我们在拉维拉迪
Bajirao, this isn't Pune... We are in Ravelkhedi.
你在发烧
You are burning up!
玛斯塔妮
Mastani!
她在路上，巴拉吉
She is on her way, Bajirao.
你应该卧床休息
You've been advised bed rest.
巴拉吉
Bajirao!
敌人...
The enemy...
没有人
No one's there!
举着黑旗的敌人
Enemy with black flags!
什么敌人？
Which enemy?
命运...
Destiny...
神...
God...
不能带走玛斯塔妮
Can't take Mastani away.
巴拉吉...
Bajirao...
夕阳和月亮同时出现时 我们就能见面
We shall meet when the setting sun and rising moon appear together in the sky.
天空将为之色变 一切都沐浴在橙光中
The sky will change colour, and all will be bathed in an orange glow.
欲望之风将会吹拂 雷云会布满天空
Winds of desire will blow, And thundering clouds will fill the skies.
干枯的树叶会低语 不合时宜的雨水冲刷大地
Dry leaves will murmur and untimely rains will wash the earth.
没有什么能将我们拆散
There will be no shackles of religion or relationships to tear us apart.
一切都将成为我们爱的见证
All that will remain will be the fire of love in our hearts...
到那天，我们将不朽
On that day... We will become one for eternity.
我们会在一起，玛斯塔妮
Our hearts beat together, Mastani.
直到死去
And cease together, too.
命运和时间将成为 我们的见证人
On a day when fate and time stood witness...
两个相爱的人一起死去
Two star crossed lovers breathed their last.
他们将看到陨落的 星星实现一切愿望
They say witnessing a falling star fulfills any wish...
但这两颗陨落的星星 只想彼此依靠
But these two stars fell to earth wishing only to belong to each other.
他们坚持着不朽的爱
They stand testament to eternal love...
爱情，与宗教无关
Love, that knows no religion.
爱是神的礼物 爱是至高无上的
Love that is a gift from God... Love that in itself is Supreme.